PROFESSOR: In an MDP, the rewards
come to you step by step.
And because they come to you step by
step, we need to figure out what our
utility function actually is.
In the simplest case, you just add up
the rewards, but it can be a little
more subtle than that.
For example, as shown here, you might
care whether or not you get these four
gems step by step or all at
the end in one big prize.
This raises a general
question for MDPs.
What preferences or utilities should
an agent have for reward sequences?
Now you might think that's easy.
You're asking me whether I want
more rewards or less rewards.
So for example, if I give you the choice
between the reward sequence
plus 1, plus 2, plus 2, plus 2, or
plus 2, plus 3, plus 4, which one
should be agent want?
Well, it seems pretty reasonable that
the agent should want the one where
the numbers are bigger.
So adding up the rewards will
give you that effect.
But it's a little trickier, because
there's one other question, which is
now or later?
So for example, if I have the choice
between 0, 0, and 1 in three
successive timesteps, or the sequence
1, 0, 0, the sum is the same.
Which one should I prefer?
Or should I be indifferent?
If I added them up, I'd
be indifferent.
They have the same sum.
What do you think?
Should the agent prefer A or B?
Most people think the agent should
prefer B. And that makes sense,
because if you're going to get this
reward, you might as well get it now.
Well, why?
It's the same reward in three days.
The answer is, it's kind
of not, right?
It's perfectly reasonable to maximize
the sum of your rewards, but it's also
reasonable to prefer a reward
now to a reward later.
One solution to this is to imagine that
the values of your awards decay
exponentially.
So for example, the same gem
that's worth plus 1 now--
if I get it tomorrow, it's only
worth some smaller amount
which we call gamma.
That gamma is called the discount
or the decay rate here.
In two steps, it's only
worth gamma squared.
I don't even want it anymore.
Well, its sign's not going to change.
I'm still going to want it.
It's just not going to be
worth nearly as much.
So let's look a little bit more closely
about how and why we do this.
So first of all, we've got this tree
which we might solve with a variant of
Expectimax, although we're going to
have new methods very shortly.
How exactly do we do this
thing where things are
discounted gamma every timestep?
Well, we're going to be recursing into
the tree, and we could imagine that
every time we descend a level, we
multiply in gamma against whatever the
recursion returns.
So we look at the sub-tree and say,
oh, you're worth 35 points.
No, gamma times 35, because
you're in the future.
And if we do it that way where we
multiply in one gamma every step down
the tree, the deeper we get into the
tree, the more gammas we get, and
we'll get this exponential decay.
So that's how we do it.
But why should we do it?
Well, one answer is actually we do like
the rewards to be sooner rather
than later, but it also turns out that
this discounting has other nice
effects, like it helps our
algorithms converge.
Now why is it exponential?
Again, there's two answers.
One is, if you just think about money
and investment, there are many cases
where if you have the reward now versus
later, you could just invest it
at some kind of exponential growth.
So there might be some natural reason
why exponential decay is appropriate.
But it's also going to turn out to be
a mathematical consequence of some
basically reasonable assumptions
that we're going to make.
So we did this discounting, and we had
a discount of 0.5-- which is really
steep, right?
Rewards are a half as much every
time tick that passes.
Then if we had the sequence 1, 2, 3
and I said, how many [? U-tiles ?]
is this worth, it wouldn't
be 1 plus 2 plus 3.
The first 1 would be worth its full
amount, but the 2 would only be worth
half, because it's one timestep
in the future, and the 3 is
only worth a quarter.
And the effect of that would
be 1, 2, 3 would not be as
desirable as 3, 2, 1.
And now we have this preference being
reflected, where even if the sum of
the rewards is the same, I'd
rather have them soon.
So what will we want from an agent that
looks at sequences of rewards in
order to consider it reasonable?
Remember, back when we talked about
utilities and preferences, we have
these axioms?
And we said, these preferences are
rational, and if they are rational,
then I can conclude they can be
represented by a utility function.
There's kind of an analogy
here with sequences.
And that is, there's a notion
of stationary preferences.
We say that preferences are stationary
if, whenever I prefer one sequence to
another-- so this A sequence
to the B sequence--
if I stick the same rewards in front
of both-- say, I stick an extra
timestep in front at plus 0.4--
my preferences should be unchanged.
If I liked A better than B now, I should
like it better shifted into the
future as well, and vice versa.
This seems pretty reasonable that
preferences might be stationary.
If preferences are stationary, then it
turns out that there's only two ways
you can define utilities.
And that is add up the rewards
or add them up discounted.
And if you stare at that, you'll see
that's actually only one way, because
if gamma were 1, the discounted utility
would be the additive utility.
So under the stationary preference
assumptions, we're going to end up
discounting by some multiplicative
factor.
Now, there are cases where your
preferences won't be stationary.
For example, if certain things change
at certain times, that's not what
we're looking at here.
There's another problem with these games
like the racing game, which is
they can last forever.
The smart race car, it turns
out, will never overheat.
You can see that this is possible
because if you always go slow, you'll
never overheat.
And maybe there's a better way to get
more rewards but still not overheat.
And so you have these games
that can last forever.
And so what kinds of rewards
are you going to get?
You're going to get infinite rewards.
Plus 1, plus 2, plus 2, plus 1.
You add these up forever, and you end up
with-- pretty much whatever you do
that's reasonable is going
to be infinite.
That's kind of bad.
I mean, it's good if you like rewards,
but it's bad if you're trying to
decide between policies, because a
string of plus 1's and a string of
plus 2's looks the same.
So what do we do about these
games that last forever?
There are multiple solutions.
And these will have analogs in the
further discussion that we have.
One solution is to say, there's
a finite horizon.
So I'm going to say, yeah, if I let
the race car plan forever for its
infinite road trip, we would get
infinite results and we wouldn't be
able to decide fast versus slow, because
anything that doesn't overheat
is equally infinite.
I can say, look, racecar,
you've got 100 steps.
Do your best.
And now because the game ends, we don't
have this problem of comparing
infinities.
This actually gives non-stationary
policies, so that what you actually do
may depend on the amount of time left.
And we'll see examples of this.
Another solution, no surprise,
is discounting.
If we use a discount factor
that is less than 1--
and to make sense, it should
be greater than 0--
then even if I have an infinite sequence
of positive rewards, then
there's this exponentially decaying
thing that's going to make sure their
sum converges, provided the rewards
themselves are bounded.
What does it mean when I change the
discount from more like 1, meaning not
much discounting, to more like 0,
meaning I don't care about the future?
This changes what's called the horizon
of the agent, which is when things are
steeply discounted, we care more about
achieving rewards right now.
When things are not simply discounted,
we don't care so much about how soon
they are, and we try more for bigger
rewards even if they're later.
Another solution is to look
at an absorbing state.
So if we change the racing game such
that you always had a probability of
overheating, no matter what you did,
then the game would eventually end
with probability 1.
Sure, there are some sequences where you
just magically never overheat, but
as time goes on those get
less and less likely.
And so if we have this way of
guaranteeing that for any sequence of
actions that you do, you'll eventually
hit a terminal state with probability
1, that also fixes the infinite
utilities problem.
So here are multiple
possible solutions.
In general, we're going to have
discounts, and that usually saves us.
So where are at?
We've defined Markov decision processes,
which are non-deterministic
search problems.
They're defined by a set of
states and a start state.
They have a set of actions.
And then they have a transition function
which tells you what your
actions do and with what probability.
And they have a reward function which
tells you for every possible
transition what your reward will be.
They also have a discount which tells
you how much you should downweight
future utilities when you plan.
We've also talked about two
important quantities.
We've talked about the notion of a
policy, which is a mapping from states
to actions, and we've talked about
this notion of a utility.
And so far, the utility has just
been on a sequence of rewards.
So I say, here's a sequence of rewards,
and I add them up or I add
them up discounted.
That's the utility.
Of course, because we don't control what
happens, we're going to need to
start talking about expected utilities
and have a notion of value, which is
going to turn out to correspond
to Expectimax values.